<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<registryObjects xmlns="http://ands.org.au/standards/rif-cs/registryObjects">
   <registryObject group="University of Southern Queensland">
      <key>USQ-DataColl-0002</key>
      <originatingSource>http://researchdata.ands.org.au/registry/orca/register_my_data</originatingSource>
      <collection type="collection">
         <name type="primary">
            <namePart type="">Samples and data from
                    the Disturbance and resilience in riparian woodlands on the highly modified
                    Upper Condamine floodplain project</namePart>
         </name>
         <description type="full">&lt;p
                style="text-align: left; margin: 1em 10em 3em"&gt; Remnant ecosystems in
                agricultural landscapes are poorly understood in terms of their diversity, function
                and dynamics under altered disturbance regimes, and of how these influence
                resilience to future disturbance. Understanding native ecosystem responses to novel
                and multiple disturbances is a crucial foundation for adaptive management to
                maintain and enhance biodiversity and critical ecosystem services in production
                landscapes. This is particularly significant where environmental change drives
                irreversible threshold responses and ecosystem transitions to less functional, or
                less preferred, alternative ecological states. This research was conducted in
                remnant riparian woodland ecosystems along a regulated section of the Condamine
                River, southern Queensland, an ephemeral dryland river system draining an
                intensively farmed landscape in eastern Australia. Riparian woodland remnants on the
                Upper Condamine floodplain are subject to significant changes in hydrological
                regimes and land use intensity. They also exhibit dieback and limited recruitment of
                canopy species, as well as widespread invasion by the introduced perennial herb
                Phyla canescens (lippia); however, efforts to address these issues have largely
                failed to curb ongoing degradation, potentially due to a lack of understanding of
                the key drivers of ecological change operating in this complex socio-ecological
                landscape. This research addressed questions about the drivers of floristic
                composition, functional diversity and woodland condition in fragmented riparian
                woodland communities associated with a regulated dryland river system, and embedded
                in a production landscape. In particular, it investigated ecological responses to
                the range of disturbances (including altered hydrology, land use intensity, resource
                availability, and key species interactions) prevalent in this highly modified
                landscape. Two of the four studies presented test the hypothesis that the
                composition and condition of riparian woodland remnants on the Upper Condamine
                floodplain are associated with current levels of longitudinal and lateral
                hydrological connectivity. These studies used a stratified sampling design which
                partitioned the study area into river sections, and also considered the influence of
                lateral overbank and overland flood flows, and grazing within ecosystem fragments
                (remnants). Full floristic sampling and condition assessments of mature Eucalyptus
                camaldulensis/E. tereticornis trees were conducted at a total of 24 sites in
                2004/05. Significant patterns in floristic composition, functional diversity and
                woodland condition were explained by differences in hydrological variability;
                however, the confounding influence of land use and interaction between
                within-remnant land use (specifically grazing) and hydrological factors for some
                measures, indicated response to a complexity of drivers. A third study investigated
                the influence of local and landscape-scale hydrological and land use variables. It
                used a Bayesian model averaging (BMA) approach to identify informative model sets of
                explanatory variables, and key environmental predictors of floristic composition,
                community structure and ecological condition. A novel method was developed to
                examine dynamic transitions in species richness and abundance between reciprocal
                pairs of functional groups; this method used the ratio of species richness (or total
                abundance) in corresponding pairs of functional trait groups (e.g. C3:C4 species) as
                a community response variable reflecting the relative importance of each group along
                the environmental gradients tested. Groundwater decline was the primary predictor of
                ecosystem response, with lower floristic and functional diversity and more severe
                dieback associated with increasing depth to groundwater; this result suggests an
                overarching reliance on shallow groundwater resources for maintenance of ecosystem
                resilience not previously reported for this ecosystem type in Australia. Lippia
                abundance and dominant tree condition were also important biotic drivers of
                ecosystem condition in these communities, and key predictors of floristic
                composition and functional group richness and abundance transitions. Poor tree
                condition and loss of hydraulic function was associated with secondary impacts on
                less well adapted &amp;#39;terrestrial&amp;#39; groundcover species, while the
                subdominant species Acacia stenophylla responded positively to competitive release
                due to poor tree function and reduced tree density. Lippia cover was also strongly
                associated with the density (positively) and mortality (negatively) of mature trees.
                Small scale species interactions were investigated in a study which tested
                differences in groundcover vegetation composition and lippia cover, reproductive
                condition and growth habit between &amp;#39;distance from tree&amp;#39; and
                topographic position treatments in a riparian woodland on the Upper Condamine
                floodplain. Sampling was conducted along twelve transects extending from the base of
                mature Eucalyptus camaldulensis/E. tereticornis trees into canopy gaps. Results
                indicated that scattered trees play a significant role in facilitating the abundance
                and condition of lippia in this landscape, with evidence of high lippia abundance,
                reproductive effort and consolidated clonal growth under trees canopies (described
                as a &amp;#39;halo&amp;#39; effect). This interaction is likely to play a
                significant role in the persistence of this mesic, though highly adaptive, species
                in this drought prone landscape. Lippia cover greater than approximately 20% was
                also found to have a significant impact on the abundance and diversity of non-lippia
                species in these grassy woodlands. Results of this research are synthesised in a
                conceptual resilience-based state and transition &amp;#39;riparian woodland
                response&amp;#39; model identifying three critical transitions for riparian
                ecosystem condition and function related to effectively irreversible changes in the
                landscape: (i) transformation to a lippia-invaded landscape with the introduction,
                establishment and spread of lippia on the floodplain; (ii) transformation from
                riparian communities which are well buffered against drought, due to connection with
                shallow groundwater, to communities reliant on and susceptible to stochastic
                climatic variability; and (iii) population failure in the dominant functional canopy
                species complex, Eucalyptus camaldulensis/E. tereticornis, and transformation to
                non-eucalypt-dominant floodplain ecosystem types such as Acacia stenophylla-dominant
                woodlands, floodplain grasslands or lippia-dominant herblands with significantly
                reduced capacity to provide essential ecosystems services in riparian contexts. In
                conclusion, this research indicates that observed condition in riparian woodlands on
                the Upper Condamine floodplain is an integrated response to a range of disturbances,
                but that certain changes (in particular, groundwater decline due to overextraction
                in combination with extended drought) may be critical to the long-term persistence
                and function of these remnants. This study indicates the importance of systems-based
                empirical research to developing better understanding of the function and dynamics
                of remnant ecosystems in highly modified landscapes subject to both natural and
                anthropogenic disturbance regimes. The resilience-based approach also focuses
                attention on the key drivers of stability and critical transitions in these complex
                socio-ecological systems. Such research is vital to evaluating and predicting
                changes in remnant native ecosystems and the provision of important ecosystem
                services, and as a basis for adaptive management in multi-use production
                landscapes.&lt;/p&gt; </description>
         <rights>
            <accessRights>Negotiated
                    access</accessRights>
         </rights>
         <identifier type="local">USQ-DataColl-0002</identifier>
         <location>
            <address>
               <electronic type="email">
                  <value>Kathryn.Reardon-Smith@usq.edu.au</value>
               </electronic>
               <physical type="streetAddress">
                  <addressPart type="text">Australian Centre for Sustainable Catchments (ACSC) University of Southern Queensland Toowoomba Qld 4350 Australia</addressPart>
               </physical>
            </address>
         </location>
         <relatedObject>
            <key>USQ-Party-559</key>
            <relation type="isOutputOf">
               <url/>
            </relation>
         </relatedObject>
         <subject type="anzsrc-for">060208</subject>
         <subject type="anzsrc-for">050104</subject>
         <coverage>
            <temporal>
               <date type="dateFrom" dateFormat="W3CDTF">2004-02-01T00:00:00Z</date>
               <date type="dateTo" dateFormat="W3CDTF">2011-11-30T00:00:00Z</date>
            </temporal>
            <spatial type="kmlPolyCoords">152.1,-27.2 151.3,-27.2 151.3,-28.2 152.1,-28.2 152.1,-27.2</spatial>
         </coverage>
         <citationInfo>
            <citationMetadata>
               <identifier type="local">USQ-DataColl-0002</identifier>
               <contributor seq="1">
                  <namePart type="title">Doctor</namePart>
                  <namePart type="family">Reardon-Smith</namePart>
                  <namePart type="given">Kathryn </namePart>
                  <namePart type="initial">M</namePart>
               </contributor>
               <title>Samples and data from the Disturbance and resilience
                        in riparian woodlands on the highly modified Upper Condamine floodplain
                        project</title>
               <edition>1st edn</edition>
               <publisher>University of Southern Queensland</publisher>
               <placePublished>Toowoomba</placePublished>
               <date type="publicationDate">2011</date>
               <url>http://eprints.usq.edu.au/21345/</url>
               <context>riparian woodlands; riparian woodland; ecosystem;
                        Condamine River</context>
            </citationMetadata>
         </citationInfo>
      </collection>
   </registryObject>
</registryObjects>
